

Summary

I'm a PhD student at Universitat Pompeu Fabra under the joint supervision of Gemma Boleda and Laia Mayol. My PhD research currently focuses on understanding the use of referring expressions, mainly through quantitative and computational methods.

Education

Universitat Pompeu Fabra

Barcelona, Spain

2019 - present

Ph.D. candidate in Linguistics

Universitat Pompeu Fabra

Barcelona, Spain

M.S. IN THEORETICAL AND APPLIED LINGUISTICS

2018 - 2019

• GPA: 8.68/10

· Venue: Computational Linguistics

Beijing Jiaotong University, Complutense University of Madrid

Beijing, China

B.S. IN HISPANIC PHILOLOGY

2014 - 2018

• GPA: 9.58/10

GPA. 9.58/10
 with Honors

Publication

Liao. (2021). Coherence-driven predictability and referential form: evidence from English corpus data. Proceedings of Sinn und Bedeutung 26, to appear.

Aina, L., **Liao**, X., Boleda, G., Westera, M. (2021, November). Does referent predictability affect the choice of referential form? A computational approach using masked coreference resolution. In Proceedings of the 25th Conference on Computational Natural Language Learning (pp. 454-469).

Presentation

Deep Learning Barcelona Symposium 2021

Barcelona, Spain

TALK

December 22nd, 2021

- Title: Does referent predictability affect the choice of referential form? A computational approach using masked coreference resolution
- [Recording]

UR-Ling workshop

Barcelona, Spain

TALK

November 12th, 2021

· Title: Referent predictability and referential choice

The SIGNLL Conference on Computational Natural Language Learning (CoNLL) 2021

Virtually

POSTER PRESENTATION

November 11th, 2021

- Title: Does referent predictability affect the choice of referential form? A computational approach using masked coreference resolution
- [PDF], [Poster]

Sinn und Bedeutung 26

Virtually September 9th. 2021

• Title: Coherence-driven predictability and referential form: evidence from English corpus data

OSI

Workshop on Computational and Experimental Explanations in Semantics and Pragmatics

European Summer School in Logic, Language and Information (ESSLLI) 2021, Virtually

• Title: Coherence-driven predictability and referential form: evidence from English corpus data

August 10th. 2021

FEBRUARY 10, 2022

XIXIAN LIAO · RÉSUMÉ

Student session in European Summer School in Logic, Language and Information (ESSLLI) 2021

Virtually

Talk August 6th. 2021

• Title: Coherence-driven predictability and referential form: evidence from English corpus data

Teaching

Semàntica i Pragmàtica (Professor: Martina Wiltschko)

Department of Translation and Language, Univeristat Pompeu Fabra

2020 - 2021

TEACHING ASSISTANT FOR MASTER COURSES

- Compositionality and Truth(conditions)
- Modality and possible worlds; Quantifiers
- Clausal and nominal reference
- Presuppositions
- The Gricean program. Recognizing intentions.
- · What we do when we use language: Speech act theory.
- Dynamic theories of meaning. Language in interaction.
- Expressing emotions and other non-truth-conditional meaning.
- The relation between language, thought and communication

Introducció a la Universitat i Recursos (Professor: Núria Bel)

Department of Translation and Language, Univeristat Pompeu Fabra

2020 - 2022

TEACHING ASSISTANT FOR UNDERGRADUATE COURSES

- · Build an HTML website
- · Regular expressions
- · Corpus analysis

Work Experience _____

China's Commerce Ministry, Beijing Jiaotong University Training Center

Beijing, China

CHINESE-SPANISH INTERPRETER & TRANSLATOR IN SEMINARS FOR FOREIGN DELEGATIONS

2017 - 2018

- Bilateral Seminar of Infrastructure Between China and Uruguay.
- Seminar on Ocean Railway Construction for Perú-Brasil

 Cielo Education
 Beijing, China

CHINESE TEACHER FOR FOREIGNERS

2017 - 2018

• Teaching elementary Chinese.

Fellowships

2020.5-2023.5 FI Scholarship awarded by AGAUR (Agency for Management of University and Research Grants) 2019.9-2020.5 CSC Scholarship awarded by Chinese Scholarship Council

Languages & Skills _____

LANGUAGES Mandarin Chinese (native), English (IELTS C1), Spanish (DELE C1) **SKILLS** Python, R, HTML, Visual Basic

Courses_

Machine Learning Standford, online

Coursera

September 20, 2020

[Certificate]

The FIDU (Initial Training in University Teaching) Programme in Translation and Language Sciences

Online

Universitat Pompeu Fabra

September 21th 2020 - June 30th 2021

• [Certificate]

From Draft to Submission: Publishing an Article or Book Chapter in English

Online

February 2021

Universitat Pompeu Fabra
• [Certificate]

Statistics for Language studies

Universitat Pompeu Fabra

Online

May 2021

	. •	•	•	
	nation	In Co	ntoroi	200
Partici	vativii		1116161	ILES
	P			

The 2021 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP)

November 7-11, 2021

Sinn und Bedeutung 26

September 8-10, 2021

GeCKo symposium: Integrating Generic and Contextual Knowledge

May 18th, 2020

The 28th edition of the Conference of the Student Organisation of Linguistics in Europe (ConSOLE 28)

January 29-31, 2020

Deep Learning Barcelona Symposium 2019

December 19-20, 2019

Membership in Scientific Association

Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL)

2021 - present